Guide to the Frederick Zimmermann papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Frederick Zimmermann Papers,
1933-1959
Zimmermann, Frederick, 1906-1967.
ca. 150 items (1 box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079519
Biographical Note
Member of the New York Philharmonic.
Scope and Content
A collection of letters written to Zimmermann. Most of the letters relate to a group of German artists called "Der Blaue Reiter" ("The Blue Rider"). Zimmermann assisted in the planning for the exhibition of the group, held at the Curt Valentin Gallery, December 7, 1954-January 8, 1955, and much of the correspondence relates to the exhibition. Included are letters from Albert Bloch, David Burliuk, Mrs. Nina Kandinsky, Paul Klee, and Gabriele Münter. Also, important files of correspondence from John B. Flamagan and George Grosz.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Cataloged Corrrespondence
Series II: Clippings, Photographs and Printed Material
Subjects
Curt Valentin Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Bloch, Albert.; Burli︠u︡k, David, 1882-1967.; Kandinsky, Nina.; Klee, Paul, 1879-1940.; Münter, Gabriele, 1877-1962.; Flamagan, John B.; Grosz, George, 1893-1959.; Blaue Reiter (Group of artists); Expressionism (Art); Artists--Germany.; Art--Exhibitions.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1975 M-75 Zimmermann, Mrs. Frederick Gift
- Series I: Cataloged Corrrespondence
  - Bloch, Albert To Frederick Zimmermann, Lawrence, Kansas, 3 Nov 1954-21 June 1957, 4 (a.l.s.), 1 (a.n.s.), 1 (a.p.c.s.)
  - Bloch, Anna Francis To Frederick Zimmermann, Lawrence, Kansas, 22 Nov-16 Dec 1954, 3 (t.l.s.)
  - Burliuk, David and Mary To Curt Valentine Gallery, Brandenton, Florida, 27 Dec 1954, 1 (a.p.c.s.)
    [A painting by Burliuk is on the verso of the card.]
  - Capendonk, Heinrich To Mrs. Beckmann, Amsterdam, 29 Oct 7 Nov 1954, 2 (a.l.s.)
    [With related correspondence from Mrs. Beckmann.]
  - Flannagan, John B. To Curt Valentin, Boston and New York, Jan-Sept 1941, 3 (t.l.s.), 6 (a.l.s.), 1 (a.p.c.s.)
  - Flannagan, John B. Attribution to Curt Valentin of the right of reproduction of his works of sculpture, New York, 11 June 1941, 1 (t.d.s.)
  - Grosz, Eva To Dorothy and Frederick Zimmermann, Douglaston, New York and Berlin, 1946 1947 1960, 2 (a.l.s.), 1 (p.l.)
  - Grosz, George To Frederick Zimmermann, New York, Douglaston, and Huntington, NY; Cape Cod, Wellfleet, and South Yarmouth, MA; Berlin, ca.1933 1941-149 1953 1956 1959, 12 (a.l.s.), 5 (a.n.s.), 3 (t.l.s.), 3 (a.p.c.s.), 1 (t.p.c.s.), 2 (p.l.)
  - Kandinsky, Nina To Curt Valentin Gallery, Neuilly-sur-Seine, France, 17 Feb 1955, 1 (t.l.s.)
  - Klee, Paul To Curt Valentin, Bern, 1 Jan 1940, 1 (a.l.s.)
  - Klee, Paul To [Charles Frederic?] Weller, Bern, 25 Aug 1939, 1 (a.l.s.)
  - Mann, Thomas Dinner Menu, Lake Mohonk House, Lake Mohonk, NY, 19 June 1945, 1 (p.d.s.)
  - Münter, Gabriele To Frederick Zimmermann, Murnau, Germany, 1954-1955 1957-1959, 7 (a.l.s.), 5 (a.p.c.s.)
  - Pasternak, Boris To Frederick Zimmermann, Moscow, 9 Sept 1959, 1 (a.n.s.)
  - Valentin, Curt To Dorothy and Frederick Zimmermann, Forte dei Marmi, Italy, 2 Aug 1954, 1 (a.p.c.s.)
- Series II: Clippings, Photographs and Printed Material
  - Curt Valentin Gallery Der Blaue Reiter Exhibition Catalog and related material, New York, 1954-1955, 16 (pieces)
  - Flannagan, John B. Re his sculpture, 2 (photographs), 1 (clipping)
  - Grosz, George Miscellaneous catalogues and clippings, 7 (pieces)
  - Münter, Gabriele Catalogs, clippings, and reproductions of her work, 4 (pieces)
  - Zimmermann, Frederick Correspondence and manuscript notes re "Blaue Reiter" exhibition, New York, 1954-1955, 12 (pieces)
  - Lehmbruck, Wilhelm Photograph of Lehmbruck in his studio, Germany, ca.1918
  - Valentin, Curt Clippings, tributes, obituaries, 13 (pieces)
  - Valentin, Curt Photograph of Valentin
  - Valentin, Curt Photographs of Valetin's apartment, ca. Aug 1954, 7 (photgraphs)
  - Valentin, Curt, and Marino and Marina Marini Photographs, Forte dei Marmi, ca. Aug 1954, 3 (photographs)